# **Evan Routhier**

PhD Student - Environmental Science and Engineering, Harvard University

(262)-309-9115 erouthier@g.harvard.edu 9 Kingman Road Somerville, MA 02143

My research interests include understanding how environmental contaminants, mainly mercury, released cycle in the environment and affect organisms. I have a breadth of skills applicable to this field of research through my education and various research and career positions

## **Work Experience**

#### **Physical Scientist**

May 2020 - May 2022 USGS Mercury Research Laboratory

Performed various methods for collecting, preparing and analyzing environmental samples.

- Trace metal clean sampling techniques for soils, sediments, waters and hiota
- Total mercury analysis (GS-MS), methyl mercury analysis (GC-MS, ICP-MS) and mercury isotope analysis (MC-ICP-MC) plus required sample preparation for each analysis.
- · Manuscript and report preparation and reviewing.

#### Student Trainee

May 2020 - May 2022 USGS Mercury Research Laboratory

Learned methods and techniqes used by the mercury research laboratory during undergraduate studies in preparation for full time employment.

## Research Experience

### **Aquatic Toxicology**

February 2017 - May, 2019 Karasov group; UW - Madison

Lethal and sublethal effects of the herbicide 2,4-Dichloropheoxyacetic acid on model organisms and native Wisconsin fish species

- Animal husbandry (tanked fish)
- Enzyme linked immunosorbent assays for cortisol concentrations
- Data analysis and statistics

#### **Publications**

Routhier, E.J., Janssen, S.E., Tate, M.T., Ogorek, J.M., DeWild, J.F., and Krabbenhoft, D.P., 2022, Assessment of mercury in sediments and waters of Grubers Grove Bay, Wisconsin: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2022–1051, 20 p., https://doi.org/10.3133/ofr20221051.

#### **Education**

BS Biochemistry
BS Environmental Sciences

University of Wisconsin - Madison | 2020 Ph.D. student in Environmental

Harvard University | Cambridge, MA

#### **Awards and Honors**

Science and Engineering

Holstrom Environmental Research Fellowship (2018) NSF GRFP Honorable Mention (2022) Eagle Scout (2016)

#### **Affiliations**

National Eagle Scout Association

2016-2020

UW - Madison CALS Health and Research Society 2016-2020

UW - Madison Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 2017-2020

UW - Madison Environmental Sciences Organization 2016-2019

Slow Food UW 2016-2019

#### References

Elsie Sunderland

Harvard University 617-496-0858 ems@seas.harvard.edu

Sarah Janssen PhD

United States Geological Survey 608-663-5162 sjanssen@usgs.gov